Osvaldo Velazquez Gonzalez

+52 961 192 6030 | osvaldodvego@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/osvaldovg | github.com/valdolab Languages: English (professional proficiency), Spanish

Summary

Dedicated Data Scientist, ML, and Software engineer with over 5 years of experience. Expertise in **predictive model development**, **deployment**, **and implementation** of artificial intelligence algorithms and methods. I have used **Python**, **SQL**, **Matlab**, and **R** throughout my career. Experienced in **NLP**, **Large Language Models** (**LLM**), time series analysis, ETL process, and tabular data for classic classification and regression. I have used cloud computing for production ML models, such as **AWS** and **Azure**.

EXPERIENCE

Senior Data Scientist

 $Feb\ 2023-Present$

EnhanceIT

Atlanta, USA

- Development end-to-end of a **churn prediction model** for insurance service applying XGBoost and AutoPilot in AWS SageMaker using demographic information about the customer.
- Development of a sentiment analysis model, and NLP solutions applying transformers, and transfer learning, development using **DataBricks** and **Python** in **Azure Cloud**.
- Development of a **text Generative model** to assist in the generation of product descriptions applying LLM, such as GPT3.5 Turbo. Development with **Python**, and **TensorFlow**.
- Collaborate with ML engineers, data engineers, and stakeholders to develop data and models in an accurate manner.
- Deploying and monitoring ML models in order to report and track model performance during the time.

Data Scientist and MLOps Engineer

Aug 2022 - Feb 2023

Guadalajara, Mexico

Tata Consultancy services (Goldman Sachs Group, Inc. Client)

- Migrated to AWS, and deployed ML classification models to identify high-risk clients and opportunities using **XGBoost**, and **Random Forest**.
- Development of pipelines of machine learning functions, such as pre-processing techniques, adapting and processing the data to call the endpoint of the model, ensuring reliable **model deployment**, and monitoring.
- Development of automated **pipelines** of the re-training process of machine learning models in production using SageMaker.

Machine Learning Research Assistant

Sep 2020 - Aug 2022

Centro de Investigación en Computación, IPN

Mexico City, Mexico

- Designed a novel Machine Learning algorithm to deal efficiently with class imbalance, with higher performance of various state-of-the-art models.
- Implemented several ML models, like k-NN, RandomForest, C4.5, MLP, Naive Bayes, and SVM in order to predict and pre-diagnose several respiratory diseases.
- Proposed and conducted ML research experiments applying post-hoc methods like **Friedman and Holm** to evaluate designed models against state-of-the-art models, applying data cleaning algorithms, feature selection, feature extraction, and feature engineering techniques.

Data Analyst

Oct 2019 - Sep 2020

Subsecretaría de Educación Federalizada de Chiapas (SEF)

Tuxtla Gutiérrez, Mexico

- Cleansed and prepared datasets, ensuring data integrity and reliability. Conducted intricate analyses, employing a combination of **SQL queries**, **Tableau** visualizations, **Power BI** insights, **VBA** in **Excel**, and using **R**. Transformed raw data into actionable insights, producing comprehensive reports that facilitated informed decision-making processes.
- Played in gathering **ETL** requirements and adeptly translated them into functional needs. Additionally, designed and developed analytical dashboards to visually represent complex data and insights, effectively communicating information to stakeholders.

Undergraduate AI Research Assistant

Instituto Nacional de Astrofísica, Óptica y Electrónica (INAOE)

Jun 2019 – Oct 2019 Tonantzintla, Mexico

- Built an infant cry translator and pre-diagnosis disease interface, applied ML classification algorithms, such as kNN, and **neuro-fuzzy models** in order to **predict infant hearing loss-related diseases**, or ascertain the cause behind the infant's cry, handling classes like infant pain, infant hungry and infant boring.
- Handled with audio data, applied some spectrogram techniques, preprocessing algorithms, and feature extraction methods in order to convert audio files to easy-to-handle data.
- Developed and deployed the classification models proposed into a medical software tool to **support the early detection** of infant diseases using bioacoustic signals.

Software Engineer

Jan 2018 – May 2019

Tuxtla, Mexico

Freelancer

• Developed and maintained scalable software solutions using PHP, JavaScript, and Python.

- Collaborated in cross-functional teams to define and implement technical requirements of a web system software.
- Managed codebase using Git, facilitating seamless teamwork and version control.
- Implemented and optimized databases with SQL queries in MYSQL for web systems designed.
- Collaborated with stakeholders and transformed non-technical requirements into technical needs.

EDUCATION

MSc in Computer Science (Cum Laude)

Centro de Investigación en Computación, Instituto Politécnico Nacional (CIC-IPN)

Mexico City, Mexico

Thesis: Computational Intelligence Algorithms for Medical Pre-diagnosis of Respiratory Diseases

BEng in Computational Systems

Instituto Tecnológico de Tuxtla Gutiérrez (TecNM)

Tuxtla Gutiérrez, Mexico

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: proficiency in Python, SQL, Matlab. Good understanding of R, PHP, JavaScript, Bash.

Frameworks and ML Tools: Flask, FastAPI, Git, Docker, GCP, AWS, VS Code, Databricks, PySpark, LangChain, AWS SageMaker, Google VertexAI, DataBricks, OpenIA libs, TensorFlow, Keras, scikit-learn, NLTK.

Libraries: Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, SciPy, Scikit-learn, TensorFlow, Keras, NLTK, Stanza.

Data Science and ML Specialities. Natural Language Processing (NLP): transfer learning, text embedding, universal sentence encoders, BERT, roBERTa. Computer Vision: EfficientNet, ResNet50, YOLO. classic classifiers: kNN, SVM, Neïve Bayes, MLP, Random Forest, XGBoost, linear regression. Time Series: ARIMAs families, NAR, LSTM. Clustering: KMeans.

Analytics: feature selection, and engineering, Bayesian modeling, PCA, L1 and L2 regularization, and hyperparameter tuning. **Optimization**: metaheuristic, evolutionary, and genetic algorithms.

CERTIFICATIONS AND COURSES

Machine Learning Imparted by Stanford University	Dec 2023
Machine Learning with PySpark Imparted by DataCamp	Oct 2023
Introduction to MLflow Imparted by DataCamp	Sep 2023
Introduction to PySpark Imparted by DataCamp	Sep 2023
Database Desing and Programming with SQL Imparted by Oracle	Jun 2017